Guide to the Oregon Chai records 1994-2005
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Oregon Chai records
1994-2005
Oregon Historical Society Research Library 1200 SW Park Ave. Portland, OR 97205 libreference@ohs.org https://www.ohs.org/research-and-library/
Oregon Chai, Inc.
Coll 553
2.4 cubic feet 4 letter document cases; 1 slim letter document case; 1 flat box (16x20); 1 oversize folder (30x42)
Financial and marketing records of the firm Oregon Chai, along with press material about the company. Oregon Chai was a tea company that was founded in Portland, Oregon, in 1994, and sold to Kerry Foods in 2004.
Collection is open for research.
Gift of Theodora McMillen, May 2016 (Lib. Acc. 28827).
Collection is arranged in five series: Series 1. Administrative records; Series 2. Dealings with other companies; Series 3. Marketing and sales records; Series 4. Press and publicity materials; Series 5. Other materials.
Oregon Chai was founded in 1994 in Portland, Oregon, by the mother-daughter team Theodora McMillen and Heather McMillen. The company quickly became successful, and in 2004 the McMillens sold it to the Irish firm Kerry Foods.
The collection consists of records and publicity material regarding the firm Oregon Chai. The company's records include notes from its startup, incorporation papers, financial audits, investment documents, board minutes, and staff meeting notes. The collection also contains correspondence between Oregon Chai and other companies, including documents relating to Oregon Chai's sale to Kerry Foods; sales figures; marketing strategies; and advertising material. Press materials include articles which ran in trade magazines, and in publications such as Men's Journal, the Wall Street Journal, and the Oregonian. Additional materials include letterheads and unassembled Oregon Chai cartons and boxes.
Videotape cassettes were separated to Moving Image Collections, Oregon Historical Society Research Library. Model of Oregon Chai carton was separated to Museum Collections, Oregon Historical Society.
McMillen, Theodora Jo; McMillen, Heather
Oregon Chai, Inc.
Business enterprises--Oregon--Portland; Tea trade--Oregon--Portland
Businesses and Corporations; Foods and Nutrition
business records; clippings (information artifacts); magazines (periodicals)
- Administrative records, 1994-2004; Series 1
  - Start-up notes, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - License and incorporation, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trademark registration, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Small Business Administration loan, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Distribution, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Warehousing, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Co-packer, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Loan insurance, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Non-disclosure papers, 1997-1998; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial audits, 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Early income and expense reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Investment decisions, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Venture capital strategies, 1996; 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Long-range planning, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stock incentive plan, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Shareholder meetings, 1995; 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Shareholder meeting, 1999 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board minutes, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Staff meetings, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Job analysis, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Employee job descriptions, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ingredients, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ready-to-drink proposals, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tests on Prisma Chai product, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Dealings with other companies, 1994-2005; Series 2
  - Starbucks proposal, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with Longbottom Distributors, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Production agreement with Sunshine Dairy Foods, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sunshine Dairy, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Offer to purchase by Swander, Pace, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sale to Kerry Foods, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Marketing and sales records, 1994-1998; Series 3
  - Sales pitches, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Advertising ideas, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Artwork, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Sales packets, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Small posters, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Feature Drink" kit, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Posters and mobile displays, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Point of Sale advertising, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Advertising materials from scrapbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Small facts sheet, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Product descriptions, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chai recipes for marketing, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cool Chai recipe cards, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Demo instructions, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sales figures, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sales projections, 1995; 1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sales, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Consumer and marketing analysis, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Marketing analyses, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sales data from Spence Information Services (SPINS), 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Marketing strategies, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Marketing letter, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Customer lists and notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Press and publicity materials, 1994-2005; Series 4
  - Press release, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Press coverage, 1994-2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Daily Journal of Commerce article, 1994 November 8 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tonic article, 1995 January 12 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Portland State University Daily Vanguard article, 1995 March 8 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Wall Street Journal article, 1995 June 21 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Newsweek article, 1995 August (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Oregon Business article, 1997 April (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Tea and Coffee Trade Journal article, 1997 July (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Inc. magazine article, 1997 September (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Portland Seen article, 1999 January (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - San Francisco Chronicle article, 1999 March 17 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Portland Business Journal article, 1999 June 11 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Coverage in Skywest magazine, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Coverage in Inc. magazine, 2001 January (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous articles, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper articles from Wall Street Journal, Business Journal, and the Oregonian, 1995-2005 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Men's Journal articles, 1996 April; 1997 September (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Testimonials, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Publicity materials from scrapbook, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Other materials, circa 1994-2005; Series 5
  - Article about chai in Fresh Cup magazine, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Product UPC codes, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Packaging, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Letterhead, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Alternative letterhead, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Labels, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Table tents, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Oregon Chai stickers, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Product Award stickers, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Borders Books label for book "Nirvana in a Cup: The Founding of Oregon Chai", undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Unassembled cup sleeves and containers, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Unassembled boxes, undated (Folder Oversize 1)